Last Updated: April 19, 2020

JOSHUA S. SPEAGLE

Harvard University Department of Astronomy joshspeagle.github.io | jspeagle@cfa.harvard.edu

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interests lie in the interdisciplinary fields of **astrostatistics** and **data science** at the intersections of astronomy, statistics, and computer science. I focus on developing new statistics and machine learning techniques to study **stars, galaxies, and other astronomical phenomena** using large datasets in order to better understand how galaxies like our own Milky Way evolve.

POSITIONS

Dunlap Postdoctoral Fellow: Dunlap Institute, University of Toronto	2020-present
Banting Postdoctoral Fellow: Statistical Sciences, University of Toronto	2020-present
Project Academic Support Staff: Kavli IPMU, University of Tokyo	2015-2016

EDUCATION

Harvard University: PhD in Astronomy	2016-2020
Advisers: Doug Finkbeiner, Charlie Conroy, and Daniel Eisenstein (with Alyssa Goodman)	
Harvard University: MA in Astronomy	2016-2020
Advisers: Daniel Eisenstein (with Alexie Leauthaud; UCSC)	
Harvard University: BA in Astrophysics and Physics	2011-2015

AWARDS & HONORS

Banting Postdoctoral Fellowship	2020
Dunlap Postdoctoral Fellowship	2020
MPIA Postdoctoral Fellowship (declined)	2020
Department of Astronomy Teaching Award (Harvard)	Spring 2018
Certificate of Distinction in Teaching (Harvard)	Spring 2017, 18; Fall 2018
NSF Graduate Research Fellowship	2016

TEACHING

I have a strong interest in undergraduate and graduate education and pedagogy, with a focus on skills such as **programming**, **statistics**, **and data science** that are invaluable across a wide range of disciplines but too often not taught as part of a typical science curriculum.

Harvard: Teaching Fellow

ASTRON 22: The Unity of Science: From the Big Bang to the Brontosaurus and Beyond	Spring 2020
ASTRON 191: Astrophysics Laboratory	Spring 2019
ASTRON 17: Galactic and Extragalactic Astronomy	Fall 2018
ASTRON 130: Cosmology	Spring 2018
ASTRON 16: Stellar and Planetary Astronomy	Spring 2017

Introduction to Programming in Python

Summer 2017, 18, 19

PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES

CfA Machine Learning Journal Club: Founder and Organizer

2017-2020

Manuscript Referee: ApJ, ApJL, AJ, A&A, MNRAS

2014-present

RECENT PRESENTATIONS

Villanova: Colloquium

October 2019

Exploring the Galaxy Near and Far in the Age of Gaia

Harvard: Summer Colloquium (joint with Catherine Zucker)

June 2019

Charting Nearby Molecular Clouds with Gaia: A New Map of Our Local Interstellar Medium

GitHub Satellite 2019: Keynote Address Participant

May 2019

Invited for open source code contributions (dynesty) in the analysis of the supermassive black hole in M87 by the Even Horizon Telescope collaboration

Cambridge: Data Intensive Science Seminar

April 2019

Mapping the 3-D Distribution of Dust in the Milky Way with Stellar Photometry

Harvard: CMSA Big Data Conference

August 2018

Revealing the Milky Way's Dust-iny

Bayes Comp 2018: Poster

March 2018

Dynamic Nested Sampling with dynesty

UMass Amherst: Data Science Tea

October 2017

Big Data Inference: Combining Hierarchical Bayes and Machine Learning to Improve Photometric Redshifts

PUBLICATIONS

I am an author of **35 papers**, including **10 as (co-)first author** (in **red**) and **13 where I have made substantial contributions** (in **blue**). These papers have over **1800 citations** (<u>h-index=17</u>), including over **650 citations** (<u>h-index=7</u>) for papers where I am (co-)first author.

My papers can be found online on <u>arxiv</u> and <u>ADS</u>.

In Preparation

37. Speagle, J. S.; Zucker, C.; Cargile, P. A.; Bonaca, A.; Johnson, B. D.; Beane, A.; Kamdar, H.; Dotter, A.; Conroy, C.; Green, G. M.; Schlafly, E. F.; Finkbeiner, D. P.; Rix, H.-W.; & Goodman, A.

Mapping the Milky Way in 5-D with 120 Million Stars at High Galactic Latitudes

36. Speagle, J. S.; Zucker, C.; Cargile, P. A.; Johnson, B. D.; Beane, G.; Green, G. M.; Schlafly, E. F.; Finkbeiner, D. P.; Dotter, A.; Bonaca, A.; Conroy, C.; Rix, H.-W.; Goodman, A. A.; & Eisenstein, D. J.

Deriving Stellar Properties, Distances, and Reddenings from Photometry and Astrometry with brutus

Submitted

35. Cabrera-Ziri, I.; Speagle, J. S.; Dalessandro, E.; Usher, C.; Bastian, N. J.; Salaris, M.; Martocchia, S.; Kozhurina-Platais, V.; Niederhofer, F.; Lardo, C.; & Larsen, S. S., MNRAS Searching for Globular Cluster Chemical Anomalies on the Main Sequence of a Young Massive Cluster

2020

- 34. Bonaca, A.; Conroy, C.; Hogg, D. W.; Cargile, P. A.; Caldwell, N.; Naidu, R. P.; Price-Whelan, A. M.; **Speagle, J. S.**; & Johnson, B. D., **ApJL**High-Resolution Spectroscopy of the GD-1 Stellar Stream Localizes the Perturber Near the Orbital Plane of Sagittarius
- 33. Leja, J.; Speagle, J. S.; Johnson, B. D.; Conroy, C.; van Dokkum, P.; & Franx, M., ApJ A New Census of the 0.2 < z < 3.0 Universe, Part I: The Stellar Mass Function
- **32. Portillo, S. K. N. & Speagle, J. S.**; & Finkbeiner, D. P., **AJ** *Photometric Biases in Modern Surveys*
- 31. Speagle, J. S., MNRAS

 dynesty: A Dynamic Nested Sampling Package for Estimating Bayesian Posteriors and Evidences
- 30. Alves, J.; Zucker, C.; Goodman, A. A.; Speagle, J. S.; Meingast, S.; Robitaille, T.; Finkbeiner, D. P.; Schlafly, E. F.; & Green, G. M., Nature

 Discovery of a Galactic-scale gas wave in the Solar Neighborhood

 Press: Official Website
- 29. Zucker, C.; Speagle, J. S.; Schlafly, E. F.; Green, G. M.; Finkbeiner, D. P., Goodman, A.; & Alves, J., A&A

 A Compendium of Distances to Molecular Clouds in the Star Formation Handbook

2019

- 28. Speagle, J. S., arxiv

 A Conceptual Introduction to Markov Chain Monte Carlo Methods
- 27. Green, G. M.; Schlafly, E. F.; Zucker, C.; Speagle, J. S.; & Finkbeiner, D. P., ApJ A 3D Dust Map Based on Gaia, Pan-STARRS 1 and 2MASS
- 26. Huang, S.; Leauthaud, A.; Hearin, A.; Behroozi, P.; Bradshaw, C.; Ardila, F.; **Speagle, J.**; Tenenti, A.; Bundy, K.; Greene, J.; Sifón, C.; & Bahcall, N., **MNRAS**Weak Lensing Reveals a Tight Connection Between Dark Matter Halo Mass and the Distribution of Stellar Mass in Massive Galaxies
- 25. Speagle, J. S.; Leauthaud, A.; Huang, S.; Bradshaw, C. P.; Ardila, F.; Capak, P. L.; Eisenstein, D. J.; Masters, D. C.; Mandelbaum, R.; More, S.; Simet, M.; & Sifón, C., MNRAS Galaxy-Galaxy Lensing in HSC: Validation Tests and the Impact of Heterogeneous Spectroscopic Training Sets
- 24. Namikawa, T. et al. [73 additional co-authors], **ApJ**Evidence for the Cross-correlation between Cosmic Microwave Background Polarization Lensing from POLARBEAR and the Cosmic Shear from Subaru Hyper Suprime-Cam

- 23. Forbes, J. C.; Krumholz, M. R.; & **Speagle, J. S.**, **MNRAS**Towards a Radially-Resolved Semi-Analytic Model for the Evolution of Disc Galaxies Tuned with Machine Learning
- **22.** Cook, B. A.; Conroy, C.; van Dokkum, P.; & **Speagle, J. S., ApJ**Measuring Star-Formation Histories, Distances, and Metallicities with Pixel Color-Magnitude Diagrams I: Model Definition and Mock Tests
- 21. Safarzadeh, M.; Berger, E.; Leja, J.; & Speagle, J. S., ApJL

 Measuring the Delay Time Distribution of Binary Neutron Stars III. Using the Individual Star

 Formation Histories of Gravitational Wave Event Host Galaxies in the Local Universe

 Press: AAS NOVA
- 20. Hikage, C. et al. [35 additional co-authors], PASJ

 Cosmology from cosmic shear power spectra with Subaru Hyper Suprime-Cam first-year data
- 19. Leja, J.; Johnson, B. D.; Conroy, C.; van Dokkum, P.; **Speagle, J. S.**; Brammer, G.; Momcheva, I.; Skelton, R.; Whitaker, K. E.; Franx, M; & Nelson, E. J., **ApJ**An Older, More Quiescent Universe from Panchromatic SED Fitting of the 3D-HST Survey
- **18. Zucker, C. & Speagle, J. S.**; Schlafly, E. F.; Green, G. M., Finkbeiner, D. P.; Goodman, A. A.; & Alves, J., **ApJ**A Large Catalog of Accurate Distances to Local Molecular Clouds: The Gaia DR2 Edition
- 17. Leja, J.; Carnall, A. C.; Johnson, B. D.; Conroy, C.; & Speagle, J. S., ApJ How to Measure Galaxy Star Formation Histories II: Nonparametric Models

2018

- Zucker, C.; Schlafly E. F.; Speagle, J. S.; Green, G. M.; Portillo, S. K. N.; Finkbeiner, D. P.;
 & Goodman, A. A., ApJ
 A New Technique for Mapping Distances Across the Perseus Molecular Cloud Using CO Observations and Stellar Photometry
- 15. Medezinski, E.; Oguri, M.; Nishizawa, A.; **Speagle, J. S.**; Miyatake, H.; Umetsu, K.; Leauthaud, A.; Murata, R.; Mandelbaum, R.; Sifón, C.; Strauss, M. A.; Huang, S.; Simet, M.; Okabe, N.; Tanaka, M.; & Yutaka, K., **PASJ**Source Selection for Cluster Weak Lensing Measurements in the Hyper Sprime-Cam Survey
- 14. Oguri, M. **et al.** [24 additional co-authors], **PASJ**An optically-selected cluster catalog at redshift 0.1<z<1.1 from Hyper Suprime-Cam Subaru Strategic Program S16A data
- 13. Mandelbaum, R. et al. [30 additional co-authors], PASJ

 The first-year shear catalog of the Subaru Hyper Suprime-Cam SSP Survey
- 12. Tanaka, M.; Coupon, J.; Hsieh, B.-C.; Mineo, S., Nishizawa, A. J.; **Speagle, J.**; Furusawa, H.; Miyazaki, S.; & Murayama, H., **PASJ**Photometric Redshifts for the Hyper Suprime-Cam Subaru Strategic Program Data Release 1
- 11. Aihara, H. et al. [108 additional co-authors], PASJ
 First Data Release of the Hyper Suprime-Cam Subaru Strategic Program
- 10. Aihara, H. et al. [142 additional co-authors], PASJ

2017

- 9. Speagle, J. S. & Eisenstein, D. J., MNRAS

 Deriving Photometric Redshifts with Fuzzy Archetypes and Self-Organizing Maps II. Implementation
- 8. Speagle, J. S. & Eisenstein, D. J., MNRAS

 Deriving Photometric Redshifts with Fuzzy Archetypes and Self-Organizing Maps I. Methodology

2016

- 7. Speagle, J. S.; Capak, P. L.; Eisenstein, D. J.; Masters, D. C.; Steinhardt, C. L., MNRAS

 Exploring Photometric Redshifts as an Optimization Problem: An Ensemble MCMC and Simulated

 Annealing-Driven Template-fitting Approach
- 6. Steinhardt, C. L.; Capak, P. L.; Masters, D. C.; & Speagle, J. S., ApJ The Impossibly Early Galaxy Problem

2015

5. Masters, D. C. et al. [19 additional co-authors], ApJ

Mapping the Galaxy Color-Redshift Relation: Optimal Photometric Redshift Calibration Strategies for

Cosmology Surveys

2014

- 4. Steinhardt, C. L. & Speagle, J. S., ApJ

 A Uniform History for Galaxy Evolution
- 3. Steinhardt, C. L.; Speagle, J. S. et al. [22 additional co-authors], ApJL

 Star Formation at 4 < z < 6 from the Spitzer Large Area Survey with Hyper-Suprime-Cam

 (SPLASH)

 Press: JPL
- 2. Speagle, J. S.; Steinhardt, C. L.; Capak, P. L.; & Silverman, J. D., ApJS

 A Highly Consistent Framework for the Evolution of the Star-Forming 'Main Sequence' from z~0-6

2011

1. Speagle, J. S.; Kaplan, D. L.; & van Kerkwijk, M. H., ApJ The X-ray Counterpart of the High-B Pulsar J0726-2612